Hello everyone. My name is Nana and
Dukquway and I am excited to talk about
this. I've been sort of experimenting so
hopefully there'll be even better
versions of this in the future. But the
idea of the separation of agentic
concerns um for those who are super into
AI and AI agents, the concept and
software engineering, the actual concept
itself isn't new. It's just a different
way that I'm looking at the direction
that the tools and technologies are
going in for AI for engineering.
So, a little bit about me. Like I said,
I'm Nana. I really am into all things
Gen AI and AI. Before that, I was
traditional software engineer, software
developer. Um, but throughout my uh
career, I was always doing things that
were Devril or developer relations
adjacent. And so I officially made that
transition a few years ago and recently
joined COD where I get to actually be
paid to be obsessed with AI as much as I
am. So very happy about that. And my
focus has been AI for software
development. Just really thinking about
the type of workflows that we have as
developers without AI and how we can
then um integrate AI in a way that works
for us for productivity. And yeah,
so I want to start with this tweet that
I saw and I had to screenshot it because
I thought it was an interesting topic
and a great case for an entire
presentation.
Um, if the agent can write the code, it
can review the code. We're all using the
same models. I don't understand what
code review bots are selling beyond
prompts and some GitHub actions glue.
Um, I probably should have asked a
question earlier, but uh, do you raise
your hand if you agree with this person?
Are you guys doing this on purpose? Is
this like a devil's advocate thing? No,
I'm kidding. Uh, I appreciate that. Um,
I thought that was a very interesting
topic. It kind of let me know that there
are folks who who understand how AI
works, who understand how LLMs work and
are thinking, why not have all of these
use cases under one umbrella and that's
let it be what it is instead of
separating all of these different um
functions or phases in software
development, which is what I would call
like one AI to rule them all. It doesn't
mean it's literally one AI, but that's
kind of how you can perceive it based
off of that tweet if we want to follow
it. So, what would that look like? A
single agent that can handle all the
aspects or many of the phases of the
software development life cycle, which
includes planning, coding, testing,
deployment, and where you can just
quickly describe what you want and AI
can do. It kind of sounds like vibe
coding, honestly. Um, and this is
definitely vibe coding or that that kind
of concept is something that is pushed
heavily in the market right now and it's
all about simplifying the process of
building software which has incredible
use cases, right? And I'm sure there are
many vibe coders in the room even if we
have the technical skills and are using
that to build software as well. So, this
sounds really ideal for one AI to
actually rule them all. By the way, I am
a huge Lord of the Rings fan. So, I was
very intentional about that name. And if
you are one too, we should talk
afterward. Um, but my answer to this
interesting question, why not one have
why not have one AI do it all? Um, you
can, but it depends on what your goals
are. So if we think about um speed maybe
that is the one of the best use cases
for one AI tool or um one AI for coding
to handle many phases of the software
development life cycle but if we're
thinking about quality as well and it's
not just a side project maybe you're an
open-source maintainer maybe you're
working in the enterprise on an actual
engineering team and you're allowed to
use AI tools or that's being introduced
and you're using it, but there has to be
done in a more structured way because
the quality of your work, the
expectations that were there before AI
was introduced will still exist after AI
is introduced. So, how do you balance
that when you're thinking about
velocity, productivity, speed, quality?
That's why I say that um maybe you
shouldn't use the same agent for writing
and reviewing the code and other phases
because the cognitive architecture
requires specialized frameworks where AI
systems need distinct cognitive modes to
optimize for generative creativity
versus analytical fault finding.
Um we can go through this slide but
pretty quickly what we see here are
really the problems of what can happen
when we're having reutilizing this
general AI coding tool for many phases
uh of the life cycle. We're seeing
issues in and critical vulnerabilities
in production. We're seeing some
duplicated code blocks. I know 2024 in
AI years is a long time ago, but that's
still something to think about and and
consider. Um, we're seeing that 25% of
developers report one in AI five one in
five AI suggestions contain some
functional errors and there's a code
quality degradation that happens and
that's not improving. Now these are
stats I pulled from different sources um
and one of those being uh get clear and
cod's state of AI code quality research
and it talks a lot about how there is an
erosion of code quality. So when you are
an engineer and there are expectations
of actually building high quality
software, we're starting to run into
issues. And that's why in my answer that
I believe that separation Oh, did you
want to take a picture of that?
That's why I believe that there the
separation is where we can actually get
the best of of AI agents when they
actually have specialized focuses and
the fundamental problem with general
purpose AI coding. These are some of the
problems and there are many is a context
window limitations or the issue with
context in general is a huge topic of
conversation.
um how to think about like optimizing
for code generation versus optimizing
for review there those are going to
clash and those are a very different
ways of approaching code and then of
course the non-deterministic behavior
specialized guard rail with when you
don't have specialized guard rails and
this idea of if you have a general
purpose AI coding um agents that it's
kind of like a jack of all trades but
not really a master of none.
So this made me think, okay, let me go
back to the drawing board. Let me go
back to this software engineering
mindset and our experiences over the
years. We've spent 15 years learning
that monolithic architectures don't
always scale based on your needs. And
that's you know how microservices were
introduced as a solution. So that made
me think why what about AI agents? What
if we were to think with that mindset,
but apply that to AI agents? And would
we maybe then solve for some of these
problems that we're seeing with using
these general purpose AI um agents.
And that is what brought about this
really long answer, this much longer
answer to the tweet that I only kept for
myself in these slides. And that I think
that context is cognitive architecture.
Um so when you sit down and you're
writing a feature, right, versus when
you sit down to write tests for that
feature, those are completely different
mental models that you are leveraging.
Very different patterns even with named
uh methodologies that you are leveraging
for each of those phases and different
problem solving approaches. So if those
are completely different ways of
approaching your code,
that shows that each phase or each part
of what you the work that you're doing,
you are optimizing your own mind or
shifting your own mindset to be able to
complete uh that phase successfully or
up to a certain standard that would be
required to have quality in your code.
And I think that that can be true for AI
systems as well. So when we give an L&M
the context of write production ready
code that handles edge cases gracefully,
that is a completely different pathway
than if you prompt it with find every
possible way that code could fail and
write comprehensive tests.
So the model isn't just predicting the
next token. It's predicting the next
token uh given the specific framework
that you have established.
That's why I call it the separation of
of agentic concerns because I think it's
a separation of cognitive concerns.
Right? We can apply how we think and
approach problem solving and then think
about are we asking AI to do something
totally different. Maybe we can actually
start first with having AI replicate the
way that we would approach problem
solving in our own brains. And I think
that that's part of what makes the case
for multi- aent systems instead of one
agent um or one simplistic system that's
dumped into the very complex and
multi-step process of the software
development life cycle.
So the separation of concerns, I
remember first learning about this when
I was learning about web development
really. I was in a coding boot camp and
my engineering instructor told me about
the explain the difference between HTML
code and CSS and how it's important that
there's a separation of concerns with
the way in which you write code because
if you want you can have your styling be
a part of your HTML. Um, but when you're
we were first learning how to code, it
was important for us to be able to
separate those mindsets. And styling is
specifically for CSS in a CSS file.
Don't try to converge the two or have
them mixed up where you have your CSS in
HTML files, which you can do. So that's
the mindset that I then or a principle
then I then wanted to think about how
can we apply that to AI. Planning agents
will be different from coding agents
will be different from review agents.
And the result could be an overall
better architecture when the goal is
code quality for um production grade
systems.
So simple software AI for code
generation this might be all that you
need. But for more complex uh software
there are multiple considerations that
make up this framework of what is code
quality and that includes
maintainability, reliability, compliance
standards that might be on your team or
standards that might be you know across
your engineering org and a whole review
phase. So that's those are multiple
multiple aspects of what makes up code
quality, not just the code generation
aspect of what it means to actually do
software development.
Here's the traditional software
development life cycle.
And this is kind of as far as my brain
went with. Okay. But now we just need to
inject it with with AI. Here
you got the picture. Awesome. Okay.
So, here's how I think about inject with
AI is if we already have a software
development life cycle. We know there's
so many different diagrams that we can
use. But now, let's just plug in AI into
those specific phases. If we have an AI
planning phase or an AI planning system,
AI planning agent that could take your
Jira ticket or whichever um project
management software tool that you use
and reference that to in your um IDE or
wherever it is that you code to then
begin planning how you're going to
implement this product requirements or a
tasks um the breakdown how how plan how
I'm going to implement
That would be the AI planning phase.
Then we move on to the code generation
phase. Um you can think about now that
we've planned it, now we have the the
you know what we want to do, let's
implement it or let's implement phase
one and two and three. And you can have
the testing aspect of it mixed in there
however you think. If you're test first
uh development, if you're a test driven
development, it all depends. Then when
you move on to the code review, you can
do or apply code review whether it's
locally in your ID which there are tools
including coder right now that does
provide um code review locally before
you act actually uh submit a pull
request and review it in GitHub. The
point is is that there is an AI for the
code review phase. Completely different
phase that is required um required uh
functionality from the code generation
phase. And then you can take a step back
and look at the bigger picture of okay
there needs to be workflows not just um
being able to complete these tasks
within the phases but overall workflows.
If there's anything that's repetitive um
or something that's important to apply
to actually part of your team, for
example, um generating docs along with
the tasks that you're working on or
making ensuring that best practices that
you've already established on your team
can be applied. Then there would be some
workflows around your code integrity.
And then beyond that or maybe below that
would be the context that would be
important for uh powering all these
other phases the phases above it for um
for software development which would
include um agents it could include MCPs
and in this case with Kodo which I'll
get into in a slide uh context engine.
So, I kind of already went over this.
We've got specialized agents for more
holistic and more highquality end-to-end
developer experience. This is the
approach that we leverage at Codto. And
this is the approach that many tools in
the industry right now or in the market
are starting to pick up on. It is going
to ultimately be about how do you
converge or how do you integrate all of
the different tools that you want to use
or different AI systems that you want to
use to make sure that it flows and can
at least match or improve the workflow
that you already have without AI at all.
And this is a little a little side quest
I wanted to talk about was which is the
context engine. So we have the multiple
agents doing all the things that we
needed to do, but then we have the other
systems of the underlying systems that
can um directly impact and improve the
actual agents that you're using across
the software development life cycle. And
that's why I added this slide is that
knowing when to when something can be an
agent and when something needs to be
actually an entirely different um
underlying AI system that will power the
agents with more. So most AI tools can
read the code but I think that this is
more about understanding the code over
time. I have seen a lot of conversations
about context engineering and I think
it's really exciting that we're trying
to solve for this problem of context but
I'm also a little worried about how much
pressure we're putting on developers to
understand all aspects of context
engineering and then implement it
themselves just to get really high
quality results. Right? If our agents
can only do so much, how are we then now
supposed to know the exact way to
leverage context in the specific tools
that you're using, what if there so in
in that case when I see something like
that, I immediately think, well, then
there should be a system built that
handles that for developers. Now, I'm
not saying that this does that
completely without any um uh without a
developer's interaction or a human in
the loop, but what I'm saying is knowing
when to create an actual separate system
that can solve the problems that are
coming up, then I think that we're on to
something with actually maturing what AI
um architecture can look like for
software engineering. And this is a
context engine that's going to um
connect through flexible MCPS and APIs.
And it's going to embed deep codebased
intelligence into your ID, into your
terminals, into your AI workflows, the
workflows that I mentioned in the
previous slides, so that all of those
agents that have their different duties
and specializations, the output can
improve over time. Um, I like to think
about it like this context engine that
is running and you know, uh, there's
doing running like a codebase indexing
and every night maybe it builds and so
that every time that you actually are
getting responses from your agents or
expecting a certain type of output, it
can learn from what you are saying
giving a green light to. It can learn
what you're accepting for your code in
the code generation phase. it can learn
what you are approving when you are
getting the results from your AI code
review tool. And so if those are and
then you mix all of that in with the
team standards, then you get a a system
or systems that improve over time. So I
think that's part of um knowing when to
this is my side quest of knowing when to
attack something from a we need an agent
for it and this is actually a very
complex problem that we could probably
have build an an entire system or engine
for it
and we can quickly go through how I like
to think about um the phases.
I kind of think about like okay we've
got the planning agents this would be
the strategic thinking before the coding
phase and so this would be the phase
where you can analyze the requirements
um that you're given or that you have
and you can break down the complex tasks
then you can evaluate the architectural
approaches and then um create sort of an
execution blueprint. This is the plan
before act um aspect that we see many
tools are starting to leverage more and
more and the fact that this didn't
initially exist but now it does in some
of our AI coding tools shows that we are
really experimenting closer I think
we're going to get closer to making it
very uh clear that the way in which that
we separate the life cycle right is the
way in which that we can separate the um
the nodes or the systems of agents that
we are using. And here's the second
step. Um, this is very simplified by the
way on purpose. Um, the coding agent for
just the focus execution within certain
guard rails and based off of the
pre-appro approved plan that you had
from the planning phase. Then you can
generate the code for like the
implementation and it could be
specialized maybe by domain if that's
front end backend security performance
and it could communicate through shared
state not just a direct uh messaging. So
this is meant to again emphasize the
specialization
and we have this for write and run tests
and debug. It kept it very general
because like I said everyone's software
method uh methodologies are different
based on your different teams where and
when you run your uh build and write run
and tests. And then we have the review
phase. Um this is all about enforcing
the code quality standards. this is kind
of this is your own your own QA before
an actual you know QA engineer gets a
hold of anything. Um so the review
agents can focus on quality and style
consistency and maybe there are other um
aspects like of security that can be a
focus. Maybe that I think that that
should probably also be another separate
system or something that you integrate
using other tools like sneak uh MCP for
example. And this is a part where you
can identify duplicated code patterns or
prevent quality degradation over the
iterations of the code. Um so review
agents are meant to catch errors that
the coding agents have introduced and
that can really help to break that
vicious cycle of iterative degradation
which has been um a big concern has been
documented. Um and for reference 44% of
developers blame context issues on
quality degradation and 40% site
inconsistency with team standards.
Right? So when we are presenting or when
we are leveraging different agents that
are going to be checking for completely
different um or slightly different um
standards or focuses then I think we're
creating a process where we are
increasing the chances of improving the
quality or catching any like issues that
would have come up from any of the
earlier phases.
So why does this matter? I think this is
more than just a code base. As you as I
mentioned team standard standards, I
mentioned the engineering organizations.
I think that AI generated code today.
There are a lot of issues that we can
solve if we start to think about the
software development life cycle. If we
start to think about the ways in which
we've separated aspects of our work and
then apply that same concept um or
separated the way in which we work,
apply that same context to the actual
systems that we're building and then how
we're using those systems and that could
result in um improvement in quality. It
could result in a reduction in technical
debt and understanding these more
sophisticated architectural patterns
that can scale over time beyond the
simple AI code gen and vibe coding.
And that's it.